Guide to the Tamiment Library Web Collection on Labor Unions and Organizations WEB.ARC.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers
  International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers, was formerly known as the International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Asbestos Workers. One of the major jobs of the members of the union has long been the safe removal of hazardous asbestos-containing materials, which were previously used in many construction products, such as insulation, adhesives, caulks, and flooring tiles. The object of the International Association of Heat and Frost Insulators and Allied Workers is to assist its membership in securing employment, to defend their rights and advance their interests as working men and women, and by education and cooperation, raise them to that position in society to which they are justly entitled.
  Asbestos industry |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Insulating materials industry |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.
- International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers (IAM) Archived Website, Dec 5, 2009 - ongoing; International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers.
  The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, founded in 1888, is an AFL-CIO/CLC trade union representing approx. 646,933 workers as of 2006 in more than 200 industries, The union represents machinists, aerospace, and transportation workers.
  Aerospace industries |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Aerospace industries|x Employees |x Labor unions |z Canada.; Machinists |x Labor unions.
- International Association of Women in Fire and Emergency Services Archived Website, Nov 1, 2013-ongoing; International Association of Women in Fire and Emergency Services.
  International Association of Women in Fire & Emergency Service (iWomen) is descended from Women in the Fire Service (WFS), Inc., which began in 1982. In September 2007, WFS merged with the Women Chief Fire Officers (WCFO) to form the International Association of Women in Fire and Emergency Services (iWomen). iWomen supports, mentors, and educates current and future women in the fire and emergency services. The website includes a photo gallery, news and job postings, position statements, reports, guidelines and procedures, and other information about the association.
  Women in the Fire Service (Organization).; Women fire fighters |z United States.; Women |x Employment |z United States.
- International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers and Helpers (IBB) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers and Helpers
  The International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers and Helpers, organized in 1880, represents 100,000 workers in heavy industry, shipbuilding, manufacturing, railroads, cement, mining, and related industries. The Boilermakers union has a four-year apprenticeship training program. Boilermakers primarily work in nuclear and fossil power plants. However they also work in shipyards, refineries and chemical plants. The work involves welding, rigging and fabricating. All work done is governed by OSHA (Occupational Safety and Health Administration) or MSHA (Mine Safety and Health Administration).
- International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) Archived Website, Dec 5, 2009 - ongoing; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers.
  The International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) is a labor union which represents workers in the electrical industry in the United States, Canada, Panama and several Caribbean island nations; particularly electricians, or Inside Wiremen, in the construction industry and linemen and other employees of public utilities. The union also represents some workers in the computer, telecommunications, broadcasting, and other fields related to electrical work. It was founded in 1891 shortly after homes and businesses in the United States began receiving electricity. The IBEW is affiliated with the AFL-CIO.
  Electric industry workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Electricians |x Labor unions |z United States.
- International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City. Archived Website, May 3, 2009 - ongoing; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City.
  The District Council 9 New York is local branch of the International Union of Painters and Allied Trades, chartered in 1900. District Council 9 is an organization of painters, decorators, wall covers, drywall finishers, sign painters, metal polishers, bridge & structural steel painters, civil service painters, lead abatement workers, glaziers & architectural metal glassworkers, paint makers, paint makers and allied trades. The website contains information on their apprencticeship programs, news, and event listings.
  Painters, Industrial |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Brotherhood of Teamsters.
  The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT) is a labor union in the United States and Canada. Formed in 1903 by the merger of several local and regional locals of teamsters, the union now represents a diverse membership of blue-collar and professional workers, notably truckers, in both the public and private sectors. The union had approximately 1.4 million members in 2008. Formerly known as the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen and Helpers of America, the IBT is a member of the Change to Win Federation and Canadian Labour Congress.
  Motor vehicle drivers |z United States.; Truck drivers |x Labor unions |z United States.
- International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers (IFPTE) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers
  Founded in 1918, the International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers, AFL-CIO & CLC, represents more than 80,000 men and women in professional, technical, administrative and associated occupations, representing employees in a wide variety of occupations in the federal, public, and private sectors.
  Engineers |x Labor unions |z United States.
- International Labor Communications Association Archived Website, Aug 9, 2009 - ongoing; International Labor Communications Association.
  The International Labor Communications Association (ILCA), founded in 1955, is the professional organization of labor communicators in North America. ILCA membership is open to national, regional, and local union publications and to media productions affiliated with the AFL-CIO and the CLC. The ILCA works to strengthen and expand labor print publications, websites, and radio, television, and film productions by providing resources, expertise, and networking opportunities for labor communicators.
  Labor radio stations.; Labor unions |z United States |v Periodicals.; News web sites |z United States.
- International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU) Archived Website, Dec 5, 2009 - ongoing; International Longshore and Warehouse Union.
  The International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU) is a labor union which primarily represents dock workers on the West Coast of the United States, Hawaii and Alaska, and in British Columbia, Canada. It also represents hotel workers in Hawaii, cannery workers in Alaska, warehouse workers throughout the West and bookstore workers in Portland, Oregon. The union was established in 1937 after the 1934 West Coast Waterfront Strike, a 3-month-long strike that culminated in a 4-day general strike in San Francisco, California, and the Bay Area. The ILWU is affiliated with the Inland Boatmen's Union of the Pacific.
  Stevedores |x Labor unions |z United States.
- International Longshoremen's Association (ILA) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Longshoremen's Association.
  Organized in 1892, the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA), AFL-CIO represents maritime workers in North America, representing upwards of 65,000 longshoremen on the Atlantic and Gulf Coasts, Great Lakes, major U.S. rivers, Puerto Rico and Eastern Canada. The union is also affiliated with the International Transport Workers' Federation, the International Organization of Masters, Mates and Pilots; the United Marine Division Tugboat Workers, and the officers of the New York State Supreme Court Officers are also affiliated with the ILA.
- International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers (BAC) Archived Website, Dec 5, 2009 - ongoing; International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers
  Bricklayers and Allied Craftsworkers (BAC) Local 7, established in 1994, was formed from seven BAC locals. Local 7, and is part of the International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers which, represents craftworkers in the trowel trades. BAC Local 7 represents workers in the New York and New Jersey area.
- International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers. Local 7 (New York and New Jersey) Archived Website, May 3, 2009 - ongoing; International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers. Local 7 (New York, N.Y.)
  Founded in 1865, the International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers represents craftworkers in the trowel trades across the United States and Canada including bricklayers, stone and marble masons, cement masons, plasterers, tilesetters, terrazzo and mosaic workers, and pointers/cleaners/caulkers. The website contains contracts, training and organizing programs, benefit programs, and event listings.
- International Union of Elevator Constructors (IUEC) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Union of Elevator Constructors.
  The International Union of Elevator Constructors (IUEC) is a trade union in the United States and Canada of individuals who construct, modernize, repair, and service elevators, escalators, moving walkways, and other conveyances. The IUEC claims a membership of over 25,000 and was founded in 1901.
  Elevator constructor
- International Union of Operating Engineers (IUOE) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Union of Operating Engineers (IUOE)
  The International Union of Operating Engineers (IUOE) represents primarily construction workers who work as heavy equipment operators, mechanics, surveyors, and stationary engineers (also called operating engineers or power engineers) who maintain heating and other systems in buildings and industrial complexes. Founded in 1896, it currently represents roughly 400,000 workers in approximately 170 local unions and operates nearly 100 apprenticeship programs. IUOE also represents nurses and other health industry workers, a significant number of public employees engaged in a wide variety of occupations, as well as a number of job classifications in the petrochemical industry.
- International Union of Painters and Allied Trades Archived Website, Apr 25, 2012 - ongoing; International Union of Painters and Allied Trades
  Founded in 1887, the International Union of Painters and Allied Trades, represents men and women in North America who work in the Finishing Trades of commercial and industrial painting, drywall finishing, glazing, floor covering, sign and trade show/convention display. The union is made up of 160,000 members. The website contains information on training sessions, publications, and their children’s foundation.
  Construction industry; Painting, Industrial, Interior painting
- International Union of Police Associations (IUPA) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; International Union of Police Associations (IUPA)
  The International Union of Police Associations (IUPA), founded in 1954, is an AFL-CIO chartered union for law enforcement, corrections, and law enforcement support personnel. IUPA works to support legislation that protects and affects public safety officers. Some legislative initiatives include the National Police Officers Bill of Rights, Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA) for public employees, educational survivor benefits and armor vest grants.
  Police |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW) Local 2110 Archived Website, Mar 21, 2009 - ongoing; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America. Local 2110. (New York, N.Y.)
  The Technical, Office and Professional (TOP) Union, Local 2110, is an amalgamated union with contracts covering workers in universities, publishing, museums, law firms and other offices, including teachers, secretaries, administrators, editors, computer operators, librarians, museum curators, typesetters and graphic artists in New York City. They promote benefits such as childcare, flex-time, job classification, domestic partner benefits and family leave. They are affiliated with the UAW and AFL-CIO. The website includes a listing of affiliated workplaces and organizing committees, workshops and classes, and collective bargaining agreements.
  Clerks |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Professional employees |x Labor Unions |z New York (State)|z New York.
- International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America, UAW Archived Website, Jan 15, 2010 - ongoing; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America.
  The International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America also known as the United Auto Workers (UAW), founded in 1935, is a trade union that represents workplaces ranging from multinational corporations, small manufacturers and state and local governments to colleges and universities, hospitals and private non-profit organizations. UAW members work in industries as diverse as automobile and parts manufacturing, health care, casino gaming and higher education. The UAW has more than 750 local unions, with 390,000 active members and more than 600,000 retired members in the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico.
  Automobile industry workers |z United States.
- Jewish Labor Committee Archived Website, Sep 25, 2007 - ongoing; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.).
  The Jewish Labor Committee, an independent secular organization, is the voice of the Jewish community in the labor movement and the voice of the labor movement in the Jewish community. The JLC was formed in 1934 by Yiddish-speaking immigrant trade union leaders and leaders of such groups as the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, the Jewish Labor Bund, and the United Hebrew Trades, in response to the rise of Nazism in Germany. The JLC enables the Jewish community and the trade union movement to work together on important issues of shared interest and concern, in pursuit of economic and social justice. The website contains activity reports, news listings, and information on chapters.
  Anti-fascist movements |z United States.; Jewish labor unions |z United States.; Jews |z United States |x Societies, etc.
- Jobs With Justice Archived Website, Sep 26, 2007 - ongoing; Jobs With Justice.
  Jobs with Justice, founded in 1987, is a national network of local coalitions that bring together labor unions, faith groups, community organizations, and student activists who fight for working people through long-term multi-issue coalition building, grassroots base-building, organizing, and strategic militant action. Jobs with Justice coalitions also worked on 127 community campaigns on issues like jobs and the economy, health care, immigrants' rights, global justice, accountable development, and sweat-free ordinances.
  Community organization |z United States.; Employment |z United States.; Social justice |z United States.; Unemployment |z United States.; Working class--Social conditions--United States.
- Labor and Working Class History Association Archived Website, Oct 15, 2009 - ongoing; Labor and Working-Class History Association.
  The Labor and Working Class History Association (LAWCHA) is an organization of historians, labor educations, and working class activists who seek to promote public and scholarly awareness of labor and working class history through research, writing, and organizing. The organization also promotes labor and working class history put into history and social studies curricula in public schools, colleges, and universities. LAWCHA gives grants and prizes to graduate students. The LAWCHA also publishes the journal, Labor: Studies in Working-Class History of the Americas.
  Labor movement |z United States |x History.; Labor unions |z United States |x History.; Labor |z United States |x History.; Working class |z United States |x History
- Labor Arts Archived Website, Jul 29, 2009 - ongoing; Labor Arts.
  Labor Arts was created in 2000 by Donald Rubin, Evelyn Jones Rich, Moe Foner (1915-2002), Henry Foner, Esther Cohen, Rachel Bernstein and Debra E. Bernhardt (1953-2001), initially sponsored by the Shelley and Donald Rubin Foundation, Bread and Roses, the cultural arm of the hospital workers' local 1199, Service Employees International Union (SEIU), and the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives/Tamiment Library at New York University. Labor Arts acts as a virtual museum to gather, identify, and display examples of the cultural and artistic history of working people and trade unions.
  Virtual museums--United States.; Working class in art--United States--Exhibitions.
- Labor Community Strategy Center Archived Website, May 5, 2011 - ongoing; Labor Community Strategy Center
  The Labor Community Strategy Center, founded in 1989, is a think tank for regional, national, and international movement building, based in Los Angeles. The Strategy Center works on campaigns, projects, and publications rooted in working class urban communities of color with a particular focus on civil rights, environmental justice, public health, global warming, and the criminal legal system. They work to build leadership, and organization among those who face discrimination and societal attack. The Strategy Center develops campaigns and demands to attempt to build a world without war, racism, and imperialism through radical and structural change. The organization runs Frontlines Press, which produces books, pamphlets, radio shows, and films.
  Labor movement |z California |z Los Angeles.; Labor movement.; Research institutes.
- Labor Express Archived Website, Nov 10, 2011 - ongoing; Committee for Labor Access
  Labor Express, created in 1993 by former SEIU organizer Wayne Heimbach, as part of the programming on WLUW, 88.7 FM. Labor Express is a Chicago-based radio program on labor news and current events. They cover local, national, and international news on living wage jobs, healthcare, education, immigrant rights, the environment, and issues of race and gender. The program is a production of the Committee for Labor Access.
  Alternative radio broadcasting.; Labor |z Illinois |z Chicago.
- Labor Heritage Foundation Archived Website, Aug 9, 2009 - ongoing; Labor Heritage Foundation.
  The Labor Heritage Foundation (LHF) which was founded in 1983, works to preserve and promote knowledge of the cultural heritage of the American worker through the arts, including music, poetry, written works, theatre, and artistic works; and conducts historical research through written and oral histories. LHF’s mission is to strengthen the labor movement through arts and music. LHF affiliates include, the LHF Catalogue (print and online catalogue of art related to the labor movement), the Great Labor Arts Exchange conference, awards, and other conferences.
  Labor in art.; Labor movement |z United States |x History.
- Labor History Links Home Page Archived Website, Oct 22, 2011 - ongoing; Rosemary Feurer
  This site is a comprehensive bibliography of information, documents and links relating to U.S. labor history. It was developed by labor historian Rosemary Feurer for the Labor and Working Class History Association.
  Labor movement |z United States |x History.; Labor unions |z United States |x History.; Labor |z United States |x History.; Web portals.
- Labor Network for Sustainability Archived Website, May 12, 2012 - ongoing; Labor Network for Sustainability
  Labor Network for Sustainability (LNS) is a labor network dedicated to engaging trade unions, workers and allies to support economic, social, and environmental sustainability. The organization addresses issues such as climate protection, food security, economic justice, corporate accountability, water availability to renewable energy. The website contains information on issues, joining the network, blog posts, and the Green Workers Alliance.
  Environmentalism.; Labor
- Labor Notes Archived Website, Jul 31, 2009 - ongoing; Labor Notes.
  Labor Notes, founded in 1979, is a non-profit organization and network for rank-and-file union members and grassroots labor activists. Though officially titled the Labor Education and Research Project, the project is best known by the title of its monthly magazine. The magazine, both print and online, reports on news and analysis about labor activity or problems facing the labor movement. In its pages it advocates for a revitalization of the labor movement through Social Movement Unionism and union democracy. [Labor Notes is widely believed to have been an initiative of the International Socialist Organization, a Trotskyist group with organizations in the United States and other countries.]
  Labor movement |x Political activity |z United States.; Labor movement |z United States |v Periodicals.; Labor union democracy |z United States.; Labor unions |z United States.
- Labor Press Archived Website, Oct 15, 2009 - ongoing; Labor Press New York.
  Labor Press is an organization that includes a news, public relations, and promotional service for the New York labor community. Labor Press also maintains a website on current labor, building trades, retail, education, health and safety, and environmental issues. Labor Press produces newsletters, publications, websites, and targeted campaign materials for unions.
  Labor unions and mass media |z New York (State); News agencies--New York (State)--New York.
- LaborBeat.org Archived Website, Mar 5, 2011 - ongoing; Labor Beat.
  Labor Beat, aka the Chicago-based Committee for Labor Access (CLA), founded in 1987, advocates for labor’s rank-and-file to have its own media and produce their own labor television and radio shows and news clips. CLA develops and distributes progressive television, radio, videos, and Internet communications on unions and workers issues. They are affiliated with Local 1220 of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers.
  Labor unions and mass media |z United States.; News web sites |z United States.; Radio broadcasting |z United States.; Television broadcasting--United States.
- Laborers' International Union of North America Archived Website, Apr 28, 2012 - ongoing; Laborers' International Union of North America.
  Laborers’ International Union of North America (LIUNA), founded in 1903, is a union of semi-skilled construction workers. The union consists of a half million workers. The union supports workers through collective bargaining agreements, which earn family-supporting pay, good benefits and the opportunity for advancement. The website contains information on the structure of the union, press releases, and other information about the union.
- LaborFest Archived Website, Aug 23, 2012 - ongoing; Labor Fest